80797 Munich, Germany

Email: emmanouil.giortamis@tum.de
Homepage: https://manosgior.github.io/
GitHub: https://github.com/manosgior

Research Interests

My research interests lie in the field of systems software for quantum computing, i.e., I bring systems abstractions and mechanisms into quantum computing for improved programmability, performance, and scalability. In particular, I focus on compiler and OS mechanisms that address the low scalability, heterogeneity, underutilization, and significant queuing times of quantum devices. To achieve this, I design systems that leverage circuit cutting and knitting, spatiotemporal multiplexing (i.e., multi-programming and scheduling), and hybrid quantum-classical resource estimation and management.

Previously, I worked in the distributed systems area, specifically in distributed shared logs, state machine replication (SMR), and replication protocols.

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science (Sept 2021 -)

TU Munich, Germany

Thesis: Systems Software for Scaling NISQ-era Quantum Computing

Advisor: Prof. Dr. Pramod Bhatotia

M.Sc. in Computer Science (Sept 2019 - July 2021)

University of Crete, Greece

B.Sc. in Computer Science (Sept 2015 - July 2019)

University of Crete, Greece

Employment

TU Munich, Germany, Sept 2021 -

Scientific Employee

Responsibilities: conducting research, teaching assistant.

ICS-FORTH, Heraklion, Greece, July 2018 - Sept 2018

Research Internship

Responsibilities: experimental analysis of large-scale graphs on multiprocessor architectures.

ICS-FORTH, Heraklion, Greece, July 2017 - Sept 2017

Research Internship

Responsibilities: developing a concurrent, shared-page memory allocator in C.

Honors and Awards

Distinction DEPROFOIT, University of Crete, Greece, Sept 2018

Undergraduate teaching assistant based on overall grades.

Ph.D. Dissertation (ongoing)

Topic: Systems Software for Scaling NISQ-era Quantum Computing

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Pramod Bhatotia

In the context of my Ph.D., I investigate and build systems that increase the scalability of Noisy, Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) era quantum computers, focusing on operating systems and compiler abstractions such as virtualization, resource estimation and management, and performance optimization.

Research projects:

QOS: A Quantum Operating System

Emmanouil Giortamis, Francisco Romão, Nathaniel Tornow, and Pramod Bhatotia

[Arxiv pre-print];

Orchestrating the Quantum Clouds with Qonductor

Emmanouil Giortamis, Francisco Romão, Nathaniel Tornow, Dmitry Lugovoy, and Pramod Bhatotia

[Arxiv pre-print];

The LAW theorem: Local Reads and Linearizable Asynchronous Replication

Antonios Katsarakis*, Emmanouil Giortamis*, Vasilis Gavrielatos, Pramod Bhatotia, Aleksandar Dragojevic,

Boris Grot, Vijay Nagarajan, and Panagiota Fatourou

[Under submission];

Recipe: Hardware-Accelerated Replication Protocols

Dimitra Giantsidi, Emmanouil Giortamis, Maurice Bailleu, Manos Kapritsios, and Pramod Bhatotia

[Arxiv pre-print];

Publications

Conference publications:

Scaling Quantum Computations via Gate Virtualization

Nathaniel Tornow, Emmanouil Giortamis, and Pramod Bhatotia

ACM Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) '25;

Acceptance Rate: ∼28%

Weaver: A Retargetable Compiler Framework for FPQA Quantum Architectures Oğuzcan Kırmemiş*, Francisco Romão*, Emmanouil Giortamis, and Pramod Bhatotia

ACM/IEEE International Symposium on Code Generation and Optimization (CGO) '25

Acceptance Rate: ∼32%

FlexLog: A Shared Log for Stateful Serverless Computing

Dimitra Giantsidi, Emmanouil Giortamis, Nathaniel Tornow, Florin Dinu, and Pramod Bhatotia

ACM High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC) '23

Acceptance Rate: <20%

Posters and Talks:

CAP Off: Local Reads and Linearizable Asynchronous Replication

Antonios Katsarakis*, <u>Emmanouil Giortamis</u>*, Vasilis Gavrielatos, Pramod Bhatotia, Aleksandar Dragojevic, Boris Grot, Vijay Nagarajan, and Panagiota Fatourou

EuroSys '24

Beyond reCAP: Local Reads and Linearizable Asynchronous Replication

Antonios Katsarakis*, <u>Emmanouil Giortamis</u>*, Vasilis Gavrielatos, Pramod Bhatotia, Aleksandar Dragojevic, Boris Grot, Vijay Nagarajan, and Panagiota Fatourou

EuroSys '23

*Equal Contribution

Service

IEEE Quantum Week 2024, Student Volunteer

Open Source Projects

Quantum Operating System (QOS) https://github.com/TUM-DSE/QOS

Alpha Programming Language

https://github.com/manosgior/Alpha-Programming-Language

Alpha++ Programming Language

https://github.com/manosgior/A-plus-plus-Programming-Language

User-Space Threads

https://github.com/manosgior/User-Space-Threads

Simple java.util.concurrent

https://github.com/manosgior/Simple-Java-Util-Concurrent

Mortal Kombat Game

https://github.com/manosgior/Mortal-CSD

Teaching experience

Teaching assistant:

- Cloud Software Engineering lab, TU Munich, SS 2022, WS 2023-24, SS 24
- Quantum Software Systems seminar: TU Munich, SS 2023
- Distributed Systems lecture, TU Munich, WS 2021-22, WS 2022-23
- Languages and Compilers lecture, University of Crete, SS 2021
- Introduction to Computer Science lecture, University of Crete, WS 2020-21
- Principles of Distributed Computing lecture, University of Crete, SS 2020
- Data Structures lecture, University of Crete, WS 2019-20

Advising:

Real-time and parallel task scheduling for Quantum Computing *Marcin Praski*

M.Sc. thesis

Hardware-aware Optimal Quantum Circuit Cutting and Knitting

Thang Tran

M.Sc. thesis

Quantum Circuit Transpilation: Experimental Analysis and Subarchitecture Selection

Zeynep Erdogan

M.Sc. thesis

Scalable Quantum Cloud Scheduling: Optimizing Resource Allocation for Efficient NISQ Computing

Dmitry Lugovoy

M.Sc. thesis

Extensions to QStack: Virtual Qubit Routing and SuperMarQ Benchmarks

Ahmed Darwish

Guided research

A System Stack for Distributed Quantum Computing

Nathaniel Tornow

Guided research

DQS: A Framework for Efficient Distributed Simulation of Large Quantum Circuits

Nathaniel Tornow

B.Sc. thesis

Microservice Architecture in Practice: Debugging the Behaviour of Concurrent Applications at

financial.com AG

Jonathan Ryan Wijaya Tumboimbela

M.Sc. thesis

Skills

Languages: C, Python (expert), Unix shell, C++ (competent);

Frameworks: Qiskit, OpenMP, MPI (expert), Cirq, Intel Quantum SDK, NVIDIA cuQuantum, LLVM (knowledgeable);

References

Prof. Dr. Pramod Bhatotia

TU Munich, Germany

Email: pramod.bhatotia@cit.tum.de

Prof. Dr. Panagiota Fatourou

University of Crete, Greece Email: faturu@csd.uoc.gr